Enter the world of Pandora.
Avatar is a action, adventure, fantasy film directed by James Cameron.
In the 22nd century, a paraplegic Marine is dispatched to the moon Pandora on a unique mission,
but becomes torn between following orders and protecting an alien civilization.
Jake Sully, played by Sam Worthington.
Neytiri, played by Zoe Saldaña.
Dr. Grace Augustine, played by Sigourney Weaver.
Colonel Miles Quaritch, played by Stephen Lang.
Trudy Chacon, played by Michelle Rodriguez.
Parker Selfridge, played by Giovanni Ribisi.
Avatar is a 2009 epic science fiction film
written and directed by James Cameron.
It features an ensemble cast including Sam Worthington, Zoe Saldana,
Stephen Lang, Michelle Rodriguez, and Sigourney Weaver.
It is the first in the Avatar film series.
It is set in the mid-22nd century, when humans are colonizing Pandora, a lush habitable moon, in
order to mine the valuable unobtanium, a room-temperature superconductor mineral.
The expansion of the mining colony threatens the existence of a local
tribe of Na'vi, a humanoid species indigenous to Pandora.
The title of the film refers to an "avatar", which is a genetically engineered Na'vi body remotely
operated from the brain of a human, and which is used to interact with the Na'vi.
Development of Avatar began in 1994, when Cameron
wrote an 80-page treatment for the film.
Filming was due to take place after the completion of Cameron's 1997 film Titanic, for a planned release in 1999; however,
according to Cameron, the necessary technology was not yet available to achieve his vision of the film.
Work on the fictional constructed language of the Na'vi began in 2005, and Cameron
began developing the screenplay and fictional universe in early 2006.
Avatar was budgeted at $237 million, due to the groundbreaking array of new visual
effects Cameron achieved in cooperation with Weta Digital in Wellington.
Some estimates put the cost at between $280 million and $310 million
for production, and at $150 million for promotion.
The film made extensive use of 3D computer graphics and new motion capture filming
techniques, and reunited Cameron with his Titanic co-producer Jon Landau.
Avatar premiered at the Odeon Leicester Square theater in London on December 10, 2009,
and was released in the United States on December 18 by 20th Century Fox.
The film received positive reviews from critics, who praised its groundbreaking
visual effects, though the plot received criticism for being derivative.
The film broke several box office records, including becoming the
highest-grossing film of all time, surpassing Titanic.
It also became the first film to gross more than $2 billion, and was the
best-selling video title of 2010 in the United States.
Adjusted for inflation, Avatar grossed around $4 billion, making it the
second-highest-grossing film of all time, behind Gone with the Wind (1939).
Avatar was nominated for nine awards at the 82nd Academy Awards,
winning three, and received numerous other accolades.
The success of the film led to an increase in popularity of 3D films, and
to electronics manufacturers releasing 3D televisions.
Avatar was followed by the sequels Avatar: The Way of
Water (2022) and Avatar: Fire and Ash (2025).
Two more sequels in the Avatar franchise are currently in development.
The film explores themes of paraplegic, attachment to
nature, culture clash, indigenous, space travel.
The tone is thought_provoking.